Inventory of the Agencia Interamericana de Prensa Económica articles distributed
Hoover Institution Archives
Agencia Interamericana de Prensa Económica articles distributed
1991-2010
97019
Agencia Interamericana de Prensa Económica.
6 manuscript boxes 2.5 linear feet
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Paper and computer disk versions of articles, relating to political and economic conditions in Latin America, and especially to free market reforms in Latin America. Includes indexes.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1997. An increment was received in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Agencia Interamericana de Prensa Económica (AIPE) was a Spanish-language press agency, based in Boca Raton, Florida, managed by Venezuelan-American journalist Carlos A. Ball M. Launched in April 1991 by Ball, it offered weekly sets of columns to Spanish-language newspapers, magazines, and websites throughout Latin America, the U.S., and Spain, until it ceased operation in June 2010. AIPE editor Ball was director general of El Diario de Caracas and authored two books on liberty, democracy and corruption before coming to the United States in 1987. A member of the Mont Pèlerin Society since 1986, he graduated with an MBA from Boston University, and served as an adjunct scholar at the Cato Institute.
Scope and Content of Collection
Paper and computer disk versions of articles, relating to political and economic conditions in Latin America, and especially to free market reforms in Latin America. Includes indexes.
Included in this collection are 8,788 Spanish-language newspaper commentaries (op-eds) written between 1991 and mid-2010 by 734 authors for the Agencia Interamericana de Prensa Económica (AIPE). Most of the authors are prominent classical liberal analysts from some twenty countries, mainly in Latin America though several are Hoover Institution fellows. The op-eds constitute a running commentary on economic and political developments throughout the region--and to a lesser degree the world--during almost two decades that saw (1) the rise and in many ways retreat of the "Washington Consensus," (2) significant improvements in the monetary and other policies in some countries, (3) several good recent years for some countries in GDP growth, in large part because of greatly increased exports of natural resources and commodities from South America, particularly to China, and (4) the emergence of Venezuelan President Hugo Chavez and his authoritarian populist "twenty-first-century socialism." This latter regime and "socialism" won the backing of several Latin American governments and many individuals and marks a democratically chosen retreat from market economies and enhancement of paternalism that has deep roots in Hispanic culture.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Latin America--Politics and government--1980-; Latin America--Economic conditions--1945-; Laissez-faire.; Ball M., Carlos A.
Collection Contents
- Articles, 1991-1997. (Box 1)
  Each folder contains several short articles (op-eds) by 734 authors for AIPE, on Latin American political and economic conditions.
  - Index, 1991-1996 (Folder 1: 1)
  - April-June 1991 (Folder 1: 2)
  - June-August 1991 (Folder 1: 3)
  - August-November 1991 (Folder 1: 4)
  - November-December 1991 (Folder 1: 5)
  - January-March 1992 (Folder 1: 6)
  - March-May 1992 (Folder 1: 7)
  - May-August 1992 (Folder 1: 8)
  - August-November 1992 (Folder 1: 9)
  - November-December 1992 (Folder 1: 10)
  - January-March 1993 (Folder 2: 1)
  - March-May 1993 (Folder 2: 2)
  - May-July 1993 (Folder 2: 3)
  - July-October 1993 (Folder 2: 4)
  - October-December 1993 (Folder 2: 5)
  - January-March 1994 (Folder 2: 6)
  - March-May 1994 (Folder 2: 7)
  - May-August 1994 (Folder 3: 1)
  - August-November 1994 (Folder 3: 2)
  - November-December 1994 (Folder 3: 3)
  - January-March 1995 (Folder 3: 4)
  - March-June 1995 (Folder 3: 5)
  - June-September 1995 (Folder 3: 6)
  - September-December 1995 (Folder 3: 7)
  - January-March 1996 (Folder 4: 1)
  - March-May 1996 (Folder 4: 2)
  - May-August 1996 (Folder 4: 3)
  - August-November 1996 (Folder 4: 4)
  - November-December 1996 (Folder 4: 5)
  - 1997 (Folder 4: 6-8)
  - Author Index, undated (Folder 4: 9)
- Computer disks of articles, 1991-1999. (Box 5)
  A total of 67 3.5" floppy disks and CDs that hold digital copies of the articles.
- Additional AIPE articles, 1991-2010. (Box 6)
  Additional hard-copy articles and CDs acquired at a later date
  - Index and 3 CDs of articles, 1991-2009 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Hard-copy articles and 3 CDs of articles, 1991-2010 (Folder 6: 2)